Finding Aid for Morgan Family Papers 1821-1893
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Morgan Family Papers 1821-1893
Morgan Family
1 oversize volume
1 oversize folder
1 linear feet
Ann Arbor, Michigan family. Ledger, of Elijah W. Morgan, attorney and businessman, compiled in the 1840's containing his comments and evaluations of business and professional abilities of early businessmen of Washtenaw County, Michigan; correspondence, autobiography, and other miscellaneous business papers and deeds; also correspondence, drawings, and writings of his wife Lucy Stow Morgan, including letter describing life and customs in Ann Arbor, Michigan, in 1831; and other papers of Elijah's parents, including autobiographies of Elisha Morgan and Polly Babcock Morgan.
851982 Aa 2; AC; Ac
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. and Mrs. Herbert Hicks (donor nos. 2288, 2537 ) and came to the library in 1968.
The collection is open for research.
Elijah W. Morgan was born in Watertown, New York, on May 15, 1805. In his youth, he worked with his father Elisha repairing agricultural implements. At the age of 17, he entered Lowville Academy in Lewis County, New York, where he studied and where he for a time was a teacher. He later studied law in the office of Charles Dayan, and it was here that he heard many accounts of the "prairie country" and the prospects facing those who would settle in the Michigan territory. In 1829, Morgan journeyed to Detroit to learn first-hand about life in the midwest. After visiting Ann Arbor, Saline, Tecumseh, and Adrian, Morgan and his wife Lucy Stow selected Ann Arbor as the "healthiest" and most promising area in which to live.
Morgan quickly became a leader among the people of his adopted community. In 1830, he was admitted to the bar, and soon thereafter involved himself in the economic growth of the settlement. Morgan was one of five men who formed the Ann Arbor Land Company which donated 40 acres of land to the state of Michigan as the site for the future University of Michigan. He was also first president of the Toledo, Ann Arbor & Northern Railway Company. Morgan was director of the Bank of Washtenaw (1836-1839), and in 1896, he helped to found Ann Arbor Savings Bank. Morgan also held many county offices. He was prosecuting attorney, alderman, member of the first Ann Arbor Public School Board of Trustees, chairman of the Democratic County Committee, and was Commissioner of Deeds. For 50 years, Morgan played an active role in Ann Arbor's economic and civic development. He died January 21, 1892.
Lucy Stow Morgan of Middletown, Connecticut was a woman "of more than ordinary ability" and "very capable in human transactions." Before her marriage to Elijah she was a teacher in Lewis County, New York during the years 1821-1827. Following her marriage in 1829 and her move to Ann Arbor, Lucy Morgan invested in lands and amassed a large fortune in Washtenaw and Jackson counties. She died in 1887 at the age of 91.
The Morgan family collection consists primarily of the personal and business papers of Elijah W. Morgan, one of Ann Arbor's pioneer citizens who had a distinguished career as an attorney and banker; letters and other materials of his wife Lucy Stow Morgan; and autobiographies and scattered papers of Elijah's parents, Elisha and Polly Babcock Morgan of Watertown, New York.
The bulk of the collection consists of the personal and business papers of Elijah W. Morgan. This includes correspondence (1821-1889), autobiographical material, essays on religion and temperance, and a large section of business and financial papers generated as a result of his law practice or his various business dealings.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Business records.; Credit ratings--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Frontier and pioneer life--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Home economics.; Jackson (Mich.); Michigan--Social life and customs--1821-1830.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1831-1840.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.
Contributors:
Kingsley, James, 1797-1878.; Morgan, Elijah William, b. 1805.; Morgan, Elisha.; Morgan, Lucy Stow.; Morgan, Polly Babcock.
- Elisha Morgan (father of Elijah W. Morgan)
  Elisha Morgan was a Baptist minister in Watertown, New York. Besides letters to his son, the collection includes his autobiography for the years 1779 to 1858, which reflects his strong religious convictions.
  - Autobiography (covering the years 1779-1858) (Box 1)
  - Essays on Christianity undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with son Elijah 1858-1864 (Box 1)
  - Will (Box 1)
- Polly Babcock Morgan (mother of Elijah)
  The papers of Polly Babcock Morgan (Elijah's mother) include an autobiography covering the years 1829-1858, which contains an account of the War of 1812, as well as her views on religion and temperance.
  - Autobiography (covering the years 1829-1858) (Box 1)
  - Poetry book 1832-1853 (Box 1)
  - Letter 1858 (Box 1)
- Elijah W. Morgan
  The Elijah W. Morgan series includes a ledger compiled in the 1840's containing his comments and evaluations of business and professional abilities of early businessmen of Washtenaw County, Michigan; correspondence, an autobiography, and other miscellaneous business papers and deeds
  - Appointment of Elijah W. Morgan as brigadier general in the Michigan Militia March 30, 1838 (Folder Ac)
    (signed by Stephens T. Mason)
  - Autobiography (Box 1)
    (includes miscellaneous genealogical material)
  - Commentaries on Scripture undated (Box 1)
  - Essay book 1825-1827 (Box 1)
  - Essays on Christianity undated (Box 1)
  - Ledger circa 1840-1849 (Volume AC)
  - Speech on Intemperance undated (Box 1)
  - Cemetery organization meeting 1861 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1821 (Box 1)
    - 1824 (Box 1)
    - 1828 (Box 1)
    - 1829 (Box 1)
    - 1830 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1831 (Box 1)
    - May-July 1831 (Box 1)
    - August-December 1831 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1832 (Box 1)
      (contains James Kingsley letter)
    - July-December 1832 (Box 1)
    - 1833 (Box 1)
    - January-July 1834 (Box 1)
    - August-September 1834 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1834 (Box 1)
    - 1835 (Box 1)
    - 1836 (Box 1)
    - 1837 (Box 1)
    - 1838 (Box 1)
    - 1839 (Box 1)
    - 1840, 1845 (Box 1)
    - 1852-1853, 1855 (Box 1)
    - 1858-1859, 1864, 1869 (Box 1)
    - 1870 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with wife, Lucy Stow Morgan
    - 1871-1874 (Box 1)
    - 1877, 1879-1881 (Box 1)
    - 1886, 1888-1889 (Box 1)
    - 1850-1866 (Box 1)
    - 1869-1872 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with American Collecting Agency (Box 1)
  - Fragments of correspondence undated (Box 1)
  - Poems, essays, and miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Estate papers (Box 1)
- Lucy Stow Morgan (wife of Elijah)
  Lucy Stow Morgan of Middletown, Connecticut is also well represented in the collection. Among her papers is a class roll book, 1821-1827, and a lecture book which provide a good view of the methods and content of education in the early nineteenth century. Her papers also include a letter of July 13, 1831 in which she describes for her family back east life and activities in Ann Arbor.
  - Class roll book 1821-1827 (Box 1)
  - Lecture book undated (Box 1)
  - Common Place Book undated (Box 1)
  - Sketches, drawings, still lifes 1820-1822 (Box 1)
  - Sketches 1820-1822 (Box 1)
  - Estate papers (Box 1)
  - Will 1886 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Letter of Lucy Morgan describing in detail life in Ann Arbor and Jackson, and giving an account of her domestic duties and household equipment July 13, 1831 (Folder Ac)
    - General 1856-1884 (Box 1)
    - Janette Ashton (sister) 1827-1886 (Box 1)
    - Bacon family (sister, niece, nephew) 1838-1885 (Box 1)
    - Lucy Mervin (niece) 1853-1855 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Samuel Simpson 1861-1866 (Box 1)
    - Warren P. Stow (brother) 1842-1854 (Box 1)
    - William and Sarah Stow (nephew and niece) 1852-1867 (Box 1)
    - Celia Stow (niece) 1853-1893 (Box 1)
    - Martha Stow (sister) 1853-1884 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Non-Morgan family correspondence (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials (Box 1)
  - R.D. Parker (scrapbook) (Box 1)
  - Morgan family account book 1887-1893 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Untitled manuscript undated (Box 1)
- Elijah W. Morgan-business papers
  - Accounts and receipts 1829-1892, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Agreements circa 1830s, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Bonds, ca. 1850s-1860s. (Box 2)
  - Cases (Second Judicial Circuit) 1839-1841 (Box 2)
  - Cases (Washtenaw County) 1830-1880s (Box 2)
  - Court Rules (handbooks) 1847, 1853 (Box 2)
  - Deeds 1830-1890, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Indentures 1832 (Box 2)
  - Leases 1840s-1850s (Box 2)
  - Licenses 1863-1864 (Box 2)
  - Memoranda 1870 (Box 2)
    (regarding Toledo, Ann Arbor and Northern Railroad Co.)
  - Mortgages 1830-1870s (Box 2)
  - Patents 1850 (Box 2)
  - Power of Attorney 1840-1870, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Summons 1846, 1849 (Box 2)
  - Redemption certificates 1830-1850s (Box 2)
  - Road warrants for Lansing Township undated (Box 2)
  - Survey for Ann Arbor Railroad 1836 (Box 2)
  - Taxes 1830-1860s (Box 2)
  - Wills 1850-1860s (Box 2)
  - Additional legal and business papers (Box 2)